It's nice to see all of you.
I want to thank you for coming tonight.
There's a lot of places you could be
besides attending a seminar, home with your family
or visiting friends or having a party or whatever,
but you've chosen to be here tonight and I
appreciate that very much.
I keenly feel two responsibilities and I'm
sure you can guess what those are.
Number one is to make sure you get your
money's worth, right, when you shell out your hard
earned cash.
And I know the money for the seminar is not
the end of the money, right, by the time you
take your family out to dinner and hire
a babysitter and put gasoline in your car, right,
the tab keeps going up.
By the time you add
it all up, it's fairly substantial.
And when you spend your hard earned cash,
you want to make sure you get your money's
worth.
So hopefully by the time we
finish tonight, you'll have your money's worth.
But I think I have a bigger responsibility and
that is to make sure you get your time's
worth.
And I say that because
time is more valuable than money.
You can get more money, right,
but you can't get more time.
When you spend a day, you've
got one less day to spend.
So if somebody has the audacity to ask you
to spend one of your evenings, they darn well
better have it.
They're going to have something important, right?
An evening is a chunk of your life.
I wouldn't waste one of my evenings for anybody.
Not anymore.
Once I discovered how valuable they were.
So hopefully by the time we finish tonight,
you'll have your time's worth as well as your
money's worth.
ありがとうございました
Okay, we're going to take a break about halfway.
Not just for the smokers, but for everybody.
We can't sit here right three hours straight.
That would be asking a little bit too much.
Somebody once said, the mind can
only absorb what the seat can endure.
And I think that's true.
So we're not going to make you endure too
long before we take a break along about midway.
We'll stretch a little bit and then
we'll come back and we'll finish up.
Does everybody have notepaper?
Some notepaper.
If you don't have some, borrow from your neighbor.
Make sure you've got something to take notes on.
This is a work session tonight.
Okay, I have not come to entertain you.
As you can tell by my opening joke, right?
I wouldn't make it in Las Vegas.
We don't have a dog and pony show
tonight, but we've got some ideas to share.
I'd like to have you capture them.
Also, if there's several members of one family,
my suggestion is all of you take notes.
One will capture what the other one might miss, and
that way you'll come up with a more complete set.
I think you'll be happier about that.
Okay, hopefully everybody can find a seat tonight.
It's kind of jammed in here.
Do we have any teenagers?
Teenagers.
Nineteen years or younger, would you stand up?
No cheating on this now.
Nineteen years or younger, stand up, wherever you are.
All over the audience.
Let's give them a hand.
Hey, nice to see you.
Thank you very much.
I'm always flattered when the kids come.
I've got a good story for you.
Two little boys in school.
One was very bright.
The other one wasn't very bright.
Teacher gave a test one day, ten questions.
And she's looking at the papers.
To her surprise,
the little boy who isn't very bright
has answered nine of the ten questions.
Perfect.
And the teacher thought, well, that can't be right.
He's not that smart.
So she looked at the other paper.
The little boy who was very bright,
he had answered nine of the ten questions.
Perfect.
The teacher thought, well, something's wrong.
And sure enough, the answers to
the tenth question was the problem.
The little boy who was very bright, when he got to
the tenth question, he didn't know the answer and he was
running out of time.
So he just wrote down, I
don't know the answer to this one.
Turned his paper in.
Teacher looked at the other paper, little boy who
wasn't too bright, and he had answered the tenth question.
I don't know either.
Turned his in.
Which means don't cheat, I guess.
Right.
It never works out well.
Okay.
The ideas I want to share with you tonight.
I started listening.
To at age 25.
At a time in my life when I needed some additional ideas to
help get my life straightened out and headed in a little better direction.
I got off to a pretty good start
up in Idaho farm country where I was raised.
Southwestern corner of Idaho.
Little community of four or five thousand people.
In fact, my parents still live in
the same little community where I was raised.
I was just up to visit them
last week and they're doing extremely well.
My father's 79.
My mother's 73.
And they're still very busy, very healthy.
Got all kinds of projects going.
Unbelievable.
Land development.
They're making money.
I can't believe them.
They've been a great example for me.
They bought some property not long ago.
Signed up for a 30 year loan.
I got to be impressed.
I was up to visit them last year.
We had a big party one evening.
Lasted till about 8 o'clock.
About 2 o'clock in the morning.
Celebrating.
And it was time to celebrate.
My parents had bought gold at 125.
And they were cashing in a
big share of it at 680.
And if you get to buy at 125,
cash in at 680, you got to celebrate.
So celebrate we did.
But anyway, that's where I got started.
I went to high school and graduated.
I went to college for a year.
Year and a half.
And I quit.
Decided I was smart enough.
And got me a job and went to work.
To see if I could make
all of my ambitions come true.
Couple of years later, I
met a very beautiful young lady.
And I put probably my finest sales presentation on her.
I promised her wealth and
fame and fortune and world travel.
And all those good things.
I said it will probably be the
finest decision of your life to marry me.
And she bought that story.
Fortunately for me.
And we got married.
And I'm continuing to work hard to see if
I can't make all these dreams and promises come true.
Well, two or three years after I'd gotten married, it didn't
look like my new bride had made such a wise decision.
I'm now starting to struggle.
I'm not destitute.
But it isn't working quite like I had promised.
I'm looking at my paycheck on Friday.
Fifty-seven dollars.
And that isn't quite what I'd promised.
And already, I had fallen into the someday honey routine.
With my wife.
Right? Someday honey.
You won't have to sit on this old furniture.
Someday honey.
You'll have a car of your own.
I had already someday honeyed myself into trouble.
Well, now I'm wondering what should I do.
I'm struggling.
I'm behind.
Money's one of my problems.
I got far too much month
at the end of the money.
If you've ever had that problem.
I remember one time losing a ten dollar bill.
And I was physically ill for two days.
Over ten dollars.
And of course my friends tried to be cheerful, right?
They said, look, maybe some poor
person that needed it found it.
I'm willing to admit to
you that that really didn't help.
At age twenty-five, benevolence had not yet seized me.
You know, I'm the poor person that needs
to find ten dollars, not lose ten dollars.
But that's where I was.
I thought, well, maybe I should go back to school.
I've got one year of college.
Doesn't look that good on an application.
But I'm twenty-five.
I'm married.
Now my family's starting.
I'm already working.
And going back to school seemed
like kind of a tough decision.
But that's where I was
at that time in my life.
Wondering what I should do to really turn
it around and make the promises all come true.
Well, at age twenty-five, good fortune came my way.
And sometimes it's a little
difficult to describe good fortune.
Why do unique things happen to you when they do?
I don't know.
Part of that's a mystery to me.
One of my friends says, well, things don't just happen.
They happen just.
Maybe that's it.
I don't know.
But my good fortune was at age
twenty-five, I met a very remarkable man.
He was a businessman.
He was wealthy.
Apparently looked very happy, prosperous
to me when I met him.
And my good fortune was a few months after
I met this unique man, his name was Mr. Shouf,
Mr. Earl Shouf.
He hired me, gave me a job,
and I went to work for him.
And I spent the next five years working for him.
And during that five-year period, Mr. Shouf shared with
me his ideas that helped to change my life.
Unfortunately, at the end of
that five years, Mr. Shouf died.
But I did get to spend
five years with this very remarkable man.
And the best thing he gave me during
that period of time was not a job.
The best thing he gave me
was the benefit of his philosophy.
How to be wealthy, how to be happy.
And his ideas worked for me.
Then about sixteen, seventeen years ago,
I was living in Beverly Hills.
And I was going through all the
notes that I gathered up during that period.
In fact, that's one of the
major things Mr. Shouf taught me.
Take good notes.
Don't miss anything.
Don't make your mind a
filing cabinet trying to remember everything.
Jot it down.
If you hear a good sermon, take notes.
If you read a good book, take notes.
If you hear something good, jot it down.
If you think something good, put it on paper.
Then you can go over it.
Repetition is the mother of skill.
And someday those ideas, if you repeat them
often enough, they'll take root and start to grow.
And someday they'll show up in your bank account.
And your personality.
And your language.
And your dress.
And your lifestyle.
So he got me hooked on taking notes.
And I did during that time.
And I've taken them now all these years.
And on this particular day, I
was going through all those journals.
And the idea occurred to me, why
don't I share this with other people?
I've used it to build some of my other companies.
But I've never shared it with the public.
And I thought, well, that would be an intriguing idea.
See if I could put into words my feelings
and my ideas that helped me to make major changes.
So I thought, well, I might as well try it.
So I put the material together
that I thought was the most important.
And 17 years ago, at the Beverly Hilton Hotel
in Beverly Hills, a few blocks from where I lived,
I gave my first seminar.
And fortunately, tonight, you are
not in on my first seminar.
I struggled.
It really wasn't quite that good.
In fact, I'm willing to
admit now it was so bad.
If I hadn't been conducting it, I'd have gone home.
That's how bad it was.
But when you're doing them, it's hard to leave.
But anyway, I struggled through it, did the best I could, and
decided, well, I'll try it again, see if I get any better.
Sure enough, I got a little
more comfortable with making the presentation.
And then I got invited other
places to share my story, my ideas.
And little by little, it started to grow.
And finally, now it's become my major enterprise.
I've arranged my other business affairs so I can spend most
of my time now doing what I really like to do.
And that's share ideas, talk about
things that matter with people who care.
And now the seminar has been translated in several
languages, so I get to travel to other countries
and share my feelings and my
ideas with other people around the world.
And tonight, I find myself in Anaheim.
And I'm pleased to be here.
What I would like to do is to share with
you what I think made the major difference for me.
I don't claim to have all the answers for
doing well, but I've got some that worked for me.
And what I would like to
do is pass it along to you.
That's the purpose of the seminar tonight, for you to pay
your money and spend some of your time to be here,
is to see what you think of my ideas.
Just capture them, take them home, and
edit them as much as you wish.
Throw out what you don't like, try
what you do like, and see what happens.
But give me your attention for the next little
while, and let's go through the ideas that I think
the major things that helped me to
really make the changes in my life.
Okay.
Let me give you the table of contents first.
I'm going to cover five subjects.
Let me give you those five, and then we'll come back
and take them one at a time and we'll go through them.
Okay, the first subject is personal development.
Which is the best place to start, right?
If you don't start there,
nothing much is going to happen.
Here's the big challenge of life.
You can have more than you've got
because you can become more than you are.
That's the challenge.
And of course, the other side of the coin reads,
unless you change how you are,
you'll always have what you've got.
I have found in my experience that
income does not far exceed personal development.
Now, sometimes income takes a lucky jump.
But sure enough, unless you grow out where
it is, it'll usually come back where you are.
Life has strange ways.
If somebody hands you a million
dollars, best you become a millionaire quickly.
So you get to keep the money.
Otherwise, sure enough, it'll disappear.
Somebody once said, if you took all the money
in the world, divided it up equally among everybody,
it would soon all be back in the same pockets.
Incredible.
Success is something you attract, not something you pursue.
Success is looking for a good place to stay.
So instead of going after it, you work on yourself.
Personal development.
See, the major question to ask on
the job is not what are you getting?
The major question to ask on
the job is what are you becoming?
See, the big question is not
what am I getting paid here?
The big question is what am I becoming here?
Because true happiness is not contained in what you get.
Happiness is contained in what you become.
So that's our major subject for tonight.
Personal development.
Of all the assignments Mr. Shouf gave me
at age 25, this was probably the most difficult.
In fact, I'm still working on this one.
I think it's an unending challenge
to see what you can become.
The next subject is called Basic Laws.
And it's good to study the basics.
And I call these basics primarily
because they come from the Bible.
Now, I'm not a theologian or
a minister, and that'll be apparent.
But Mr. Shouf taught me that the Bible was
a good textbook for ideas and stories and success equations,
how to live the better life.
I found out that was true.
He also taught me that the Bible
is as practical as it is spiritual.
And I found out that's true.
If you look at your bank account
and your income and you're not happy,
there are several places in the Bible
to check to see what the heck's wrong
so you can make the changes.
And we're going to cover
some of those tonight called basics.
Okay.
The next subject is my favorite, setting goals.
Mr. Shouf taught me how to set goals.
What a favor that was.
One morning at breakfast shortly after I met him,
he said, Jim, let me see your current list of
goals and let's go over them and talk about them.
He said, maybe that's the best way I
can help you get a better direction started.
And I said, I don't have a list.
He said, well, is it out in the car?
Or home somewhere?
I said, no, sir.
I don't have a list anywhere.
He said, well, young man,
that's where we got to start.
He said, I can tell you right now, if
you don't have a list of your goals with you,
he said, I can guess your
bank balance within a few hundred dollars.
Which he did.
And that got my attention.
I said, you mean my bank balance would
change if I had a list of goals?
He said, drastically.
That day I became a
willing student how to set goals.
And sure enough, learning how
to set goals changed my life.
And I often wondered why no one had ever
taught me how to set goals up until age 25.
I went to high school, but
if they offered it, I missed it.
I went to college for a year, never heard it.
I worked for Sears.
Really.
And to my knowledge, Sears never taught it.
How to set goals.
So here I am, age 25, married, my family starting, I've been
to college, I'm working, and I still don't know how to set goals.
But fortunately, when I was 25, I
met the man who taught me how.
And it revolutionized my whole life.
Economically, socially, personally, it's incredible.
So I want to share with you tonight what
Mr. Shove shared with me, how to set goals.
It can be a life changer.
Okay.
The next subject is the negative part of the seminar.
Life is part negative, so we
got to talk about the negative.
And this subject is called Diseases of Attitude.
Diseases of Attitude.
There's a lot of things that
can wreck your chances to do well.
We live in a rather dangerous world, so you got
to be not only wise, you got to be careful.
Now attitude diseases are just
as bad as physical diseases, right?
High blood pressure, heart trouble.
I mean, a lot of things
lace your chances to do well.
So you've got to be careful.
And attitude diseases are deadly.
I mean, they'll destroy all the good things you start.
Okay.
So we'll go through those attitude diseases.
How to spot them, how to look
for them, what they are, and the cure.
And I'm a pro on these because I've had them
all, so I can give you excellent advice on these.
Now the last subject we're
going to consider tonight is called...
The Day That Turns Your Life Around.
And under this subject we're going to talk
about the emotions that can change your life.
Human beings are emotional creatures.
And emotions are powerful for life change.
Now of course emotions are so powerful
they can go either way on you.
Emotions can either build or destroy.
So you really have to employ emotions properly.
We call civilization a civilization.
The intelligent management of human emotions.
If you can intelligently apply your emotions in
the right direction, no telling what can happen.
Could turn your life around one day would be sufficient.
So we'll talk about those.
Okay.
Now that's a lot to cover in one evening.
But we'll keep at it here.
And see if we can't get it all done.
I'd like to have you now
jot down the theme of the seminar.
Every seminar should have a theme I guess.
We've got one.
It's on some of our literature
if you happen to notice it.
But if you didn't, for your notes, here it is.
The theme of the seminar.
It goes like this.
The major key to your better future is you.
That's the theme of our seminar tonight.
And I'd like to have you underline two words.
Just to give it some added punch.
Underline the word major and the word you.
So that it reads, the major
key to your better future is you.
Now my first suggestion is, transfer this to a card or something
where you can put it up where you can see it every day.
Preferably put it up where you can
see it at the beginning of the day.
Before you go off to put the day together.
This is a good phrase just to glance at.
To keep in mind as you're putting the day together.
It's called the silent seminar.
If you'll just let this
talk to you during the day.
I found it to be tremendously helpful.
The major key to your better future is you.
For a big share of my life now,
I didn't have this one quite figured out.
Among a lot of things
I didn't have quite figured out.
Many things used to puzzle
me back in those early days.
I used to wonder why two
people could work for the same company.
One make twice as much money.
Now see that used to puzzle me.
And maybe they were the same age.
Graduated from the same school.
Live in the same community.
Work for the same company.
With the same products and the same services.
They've got the same traffic.
The same problems.
And one makes a thousand a month.
The other one makes two thousand a month.
Now that was my puzzling question.
Why would this long list be the
same and the money twice as much?
I asked, what's the difference between a
thousand a month and two thousand a month?
And I don't mean a thousand a month, right?
I could figure that out.
But what makes the difference?
Why would one person do twice
as well, three times as well?
Speaking economically.
Now I know there's more
than one way to do well.
I understand that.
But in this little narrow
area called compensation, what's the difference?
Well back then with my faulty
thinking, I'm trying to reason it out.
I thought, well maybe time
makes some of the difference, right?
Some people do better because they have more time.
I used to say, Harold ought
to be able to do well.
He's got a lot of time.
If I had all of
Harold's time, I could do well.
Now that's got to be dumb, right?
Number one, you can't get somebody else's time.
A guy says to me one time, he says, you know,
if I had some extra time, I could make some extra money.
I said, then forget it.
There isn't any extra time.
Hey, when the clock strikes 12
midnight, that about wraps it up, right?
I mean, you can look around the gongs around here.
I'm here for a little more, but it's over.
You say to the guy, what are you doing?
He said, I'm looking for extra time.
See, they'll come and take you away, right?
There isn't any more time.
Now, if you can't get more time, which you can't, what could
you get more of that would make a difference in economic results?
And here's the key word.
Make it a part of your notes.
We're going to consider it tonight.
The word is value.
And I have a little phrase for your notes.
Value makes the difference in results.
Value makes the difference.
You can't get more time,
but you can create more value.
Now, here's the first lesson of economics.
Everybody should learn it from the time they're
old enough to understand what a dollar means.
How to earn one, how to get one,
how to keep one, what to do with it.
First lesson of economics.
We primarily get paid for value.
That's lesson one.
Bringing value to the marketplace.
That's how you get paid.
You don't get paid for the time.
I know it takes time to bring value to the
marketplace, but you get paid for the value, not the time.
Now, since that's true, here's one
of the key questions of the evening.
Is it possible to become
twice as valuable at the marketplace
and make twice as much money in the store?
At the same time?
Could you become three times as valuable?
Make three times as much money in the same time?
Is that possible?
The answer is yes, if.
And it's always if, right?
Life is known as the big if.
Harry Truman once said,
Life is iffy.
How true.
And here's the big if.
We're going to consider it tonight.
It's possible to do much better at the
marketplace if you go to work primarily on yourself.
And that's the theme of our seminar tonight.
Learning to work primarily on yourself.
People have asked me for the last 24 years,
How do you develop an above average income?
And the answer is,
Become an above average person.
Develop an above average handshake.
Some people want to be successful,
they don't even work on their handshake.
As easy as that would be to start on.
They let it slide, they don't understand.
Develop an above average smile.
Develop an above average excitement.
Develop an above average interest in other people.
Develop an above average intensity to win.
See, that'll change everything.
Probably one of the most frustrating experiences in my life.
Is looking for an above average job with
above average pay without becoming an above average person.
It's called frustration.
And Mr. Shouf gave me probably the greatest
clue he gave me when I first met him.
He said, Jim, if you want to be wealthy and
happy the rest of your life, just learn this lesson well.
He said, learn to work harder on
yourself than you do on your job.
That was it.
The beginning of the philosophy
that helped to change my life.
Work harder on yourself than you do on your job.
When he said that, I
suddenly understood why I was broke.
I was a hard worker.
On my job.
If anybody would have asked me, age
25, Mr. Rohn, are you a hard worker?
I'd have said, yes, I'm a hard worker.
Check my record.
I work as hard as anybody.
And that was true.
I was a hard worker.
I really was.
But see, that was my problem.
I was working hard on my job,
but I wasn't working hard on myself.
And that was my reason for lack of progress.
Some people look for more money, but
they look for it in the wrong direction.
The guy says, I need more money.
I'm going to go work on my boss.
Well, number one, bosses are notorious.
They do not play fast
and loose with the company till.
I've never seen a boss
get excited and triple somebody's wages.
Right?
I mean, they don't behave in such an irrational manner.
So, see, that's not what you work on.
Some people say, well, I'll go on strike for more.
Well, big deal.
The problem with that game is
once you start it, it's never over.
You'll always have to strike.
And I'll tell you what you get by demand.
Little bitty pieces.
Barely enough.
And now inflation beats that game.
Right?
The guy demands 10%.
Inflation's 12.
He's behind two.
I mean, it never ends.
So, see, that's not the key to success.
Maybe survival, but not success.
The guy in sales says, I've got it.
I'll get me some of those
books that teach you the tricky sales.
And I'll go leap upon my
prospects, dazzling with my sales footwork,
grab their money before they know what's happened.
Well, you can play those kind
of tricks if you want to.
My observation shows the last 24 years, you wind up
at the bottom of the economic ladder, not the top.
See, it's not what you get by tricks.
It's not what you get by demand.
It's what you get by performance that counts.
So that's one of the key phrases of the evening.
It's performance that counts.
And I discovered this.
Performance comes from inside, not outside.
For a share of my life, I'm
looking for the answers to do well outside.
Found out they were inside.
Then Mr. Shouff gave me probably
one of the most important clues
among so many things he taught me.
But this was in those early days.
Mr. Shouff was very kind,
but he was also very abrupt.
And he had these interesting questions to ask.
I'm giving him a little run day.
Run down one day on how
things hadn't worked out for me.
He said, Mr. Owen, I've got the
answer for you if you will listen carefully.
And listen carefully I did that
day and for the next five years.
If somebody's wealthy and happy, you gotta listen.
He said, Jim, I've only known you a short time.
But he said, it's already my honest opinion that
for things to change for you, you got to change.
That wasn't quite the answer.
That wasn't quite the answer I was looking for.
But that's the answer he gave me.
And I pass it along to you
on this warm summer evening in Anaheim, California.
For things to change for you, you've got to change.
Otherwise, it isn't gonna change.
Before I met Mr. Shouff, I used
to say, I sure hope things will change.
Right?
That seemed to be my only hope.
If it isn't gonna change, I'm in serious trouble.
And then I discovered it isn't gonna change.
So I'm in serious trouble.
See, I can tell you what
the 80s are gonna be like.
You have dropped into the right place.
I did a seminar one time for
Standard Oil executives and management in Honolulu.
And we're having a conference one
day on this big conference table.
And one of them said to me, Mr. Rohn,
you know some fairly important people halfway around the world.
What do you think the 80s are gonna be like?
I said, gentlemen, I do know the right people.
I can tell you.
So they all listened very carefully.
And I said, gentlemen, based on my wide experience,
I can really honestly say to you, in my opinion,
in the 80s, it's gonna
be about like it's always been.
Aren't you glad you came?
That's inside.
I don't pass that around just everywhere.
Now, of course, I said that to make a
point, but I also said it because it's accurate.
It's gonna be about like it's always been.
It isn't gonna change.
The tide comes in and then what?
It goes out for six and a half thousand years
that we know of, recorded history, and probably long before that.
So it is not gonna change.
It gets light.
It gets light and then what?
It turns dark.
Six and a half thousand years.
See, it's not likely to change.
And we're not to be startled by that.
If the sun goes down, the guy says, what's happened?
What's happened?
It means he hasn't been here long, I guess, right?
It always goes down about this time.
The guy says, well, I don't like that arrangement.
Well, you got to talk to somebody besides me, right?
It gets light, then it turns dark.
In rotation, the next season after fall is what?
Winter.
Pray tell how often does winter follow fall?
Every year regularly for the last six
and a half thousand that we know of.
See, it is not gonna change.
Now, some winters are long and some are short and some are
hard and some are easy, but they always come right after falls.
It isn't gonna change.
Sometimes you can figure it out.
Sometimes there's no way to figure it out.
Sometimes it goes well.
Sometimes it gets in a knot.
Sometimes it sails along.
Sometimes it gets in reverse.
See, that's not gonna change.
The last six thousand years reads like this.
Opportunity mixed with difficulty.
That's how it reads.
It isn't gonna change.
The man says, well, if it isn't
gonna change, how will my life ever change?
Answer, when you change.
And whether I'm talking to high school kids
or business executives, my message is always the same.
And it goes like this.
The only way it gets better
for you is when you get better.
Let me give you the four
major lessons in life to learn.
Here's four majors.
It's good to study the majors.
In our weekend seminar we teach.
Some people don't do well
because they major in minor things.
You've got to be on the lookout.
At the end of every week, end
of every month, you've got to check.
Make sure you're not spending major time on minor things.
We go through that whole series.
Majors and minors.
Now, let me give you two phrases
before we get to the four majors.
This will set it up
and you'll see where I'm going.
Two key phrases for your notes.
Here's the first one.
Life and business.
Is like the changing seasons.
That's the first phrase.
Life and business.
Is like the changing seasons.
One of the best ways to describe life.
It's like the seasons.
Frank Sinatra sings, life is like the seasons.
Now here's the second phrase.
Very important.
You cannot change the seasons.
But you can.
Change.
Yourself.
You can't change the seasons.
But you can.
Change.
Yourself.
And see, that's how life gets better for you.
Not by chance.
But by change.
Now here's the four major lessons in life to learn.
I've got my first book finished.
Came out a couple of weeks ago.
This is in it.
The four major lessons in life to learn.
Here they are.
Number one.
Learn how to handle the winters.
That's lesson one.
They come right after falls.
With regularity.
Some are long and some are short.
And some are hard and some are easy.
But they keep coming.
You must learn to handle the nights.
They come right after days.
You must learn to handle difficulty.
It comes right after opportunity.
You must learn to handle recessions.
They always follow progressions.
For the last six thousand.
See, it isn't going to change.
The lesson you must learn is how to handle it.
And there's all kinds of winters, right?
The winter when you can't figure it out.
The winter when it all goes smash.
The winter when it turns belly up.
The winter when it won't work.
When you've run out of money
and you've got a broken heart.
See, those are winter times.
There's all kinds.
Economic winters.
Social winters.
Personal winters.
When your heart is smashed in a thousand pieces.
And the nights are unusually long.
Your prayers seem to go no higher than your head.
It's winter time.
Barbra Streisand sings,
It used to be so natural to talk about forever,
but used to be's don't count anymore.
They just lay on the floor.
Till we sweep them away.
You don't sing me love songs.
And you don't say you need me.
And you don't bring me flowers anymore.
A song of winter.
But see, the disappointments come.
Those are normal.
That's part of life.
But the question is, how do you handle it?
How do you handle the coming winters
and the disappointments and the down times?
Well, you can't get rid of
January by tearing it off the calendar.
But here's what you can do.
You can get stronger.
You can get wiser.
And you can get better.
The winters won't change, but you can.
And that's how life changes for you.
See, before I understood, when it was
winter, I used to wish it was summer.
I didn't understand.
When it was hard, I
used to wish it was winter.
I didn't wish it was easy.
I didn't know.
And then Mr. Shoaff gave me a part
of his very unique philosophy when he said,
Don't wish it was easier.
Wish you were better.
See, that triggered my whole life change.
Don't wish for less problems.
Wish for more skills.
Don't wish for less challenge.
Wish for more wisdom.
That's the key.
So that's lesson one.
Learn how to handle the winters.
Here's lesson two.
Learn how to take advantage of the spring.
That's the second one.
Spring is called opportunity.
And spring follows winter.
What a great place for it.
If you were going to put it
somewhere, that'd be the place to put it.
Right after winter.
And pray tell, how often does spring follow winter?
Every year with regularity.
Regularity, 6,000.
You can almost count on it.
See, opportunity always comes.
Days follow nights.
Isn't that terrific?
Opportunity follows difficulty.
But here's what you must learn to do.
Underline these two words in that key phrase.
Take advantage.
Underline those two.
You must learn to take advantage of the spring.
See, just because spring rolls around is no
sign you're going to look good come fall.
You gotta do something with it.
In fact, you have to get good
at one of two things in life.
Planting in the spring or begging in the fall.
Or get somebody to do it for you.
See, those are about the only alternatives.
Now here's what else you must do.
Take advantage of the springs
quickly because there's only a few.
Just a handful of springs have
been handed to each of us.
They don't come forever.
Life is fairly brief.
So you got to read every book you can get your
hands on on what to do with your springs while they're here.
And take advantage. They soon run out.
The Beatles wrote,
Life is so short.
And for John Lennon, it was extra short.
But life is brief.
Elton John sings,
She lived her life like a candle in the wind.
It's brief.
So whatever you're going to do with your life,
you got to get at it.
Don't just let the springs pass, pass, pass.
Here's the third major lesson in life to learn.
Learn how to protect your crops all summer.
You got to take care of what you start.
Sure enough, as soon as you've
planted your garden in the spring,
the busy bugs and the noxious
weeds are out to take it.
And here's the next bit of truth.
They will take it.
Unless you prevent it.
And that's the third major skill to learn.
You've got to learn to prevent the
intruder from taking all the good you start.
It's one of the challenges.
Here's two key phrases under number three.
First one,
All good will be attacked.
On this planet.
Maybe not the next one we
get to, but on this one,
all good will be attacked.
Every garden will be invaded.
Not to think so is naive.
And here's the second phrase.
All values must be defended.
Political values, social values, community values,
family values, marriage values, friendship values,
business values.
Every garden must be tended all summer.
Third major lesson.
Now here's number four.
Fourth major lesson in life to learn.
Learn how to reap in the fall without complaint.
Learn to reap come harvest time without complaint.
Then take full responsibility for what happens to you.
So take full responsibility for what happens to you.
It's one of the highest forms of human maturity.
Accepting full responsibility.
It's the day you know
you've passed from childhood to adulthood.
The day you accept full responsibility.
And another note.
Learn to reap in the fall without apology.
Without apology if you do well.
And without complaint.
Then learn how to reap in the fall without apology.
apology if you do well and
without complaint if you don't. That's maturity.
I used to have that long list of
reasons why I wasn't doing well. To explain. You
got to explain right? Otherwise you're gonna
look bad. I used to have this funny
list called reasons for not looking good.
チョコレート
I used to blame the government.
I mean, you can believe that or not.
It was at the top of my list.
I had a lecture second to none.
The government.
That was on my list.
I used to blame taxes.
Look what you got left after they take everything.
And they expect you to do well.
That was on my list there.
Prices, that one's easy, right?
You walk into the supermarket with $20,
come out with a little half bag.
So I had that on my list.
I used to blame the weather.
I blamed the traffic.
I used to blame my car.
I blamed the manufacturers.
I used to blame the company.
I blamed company policy.
I used to blame the training program.
I blame my negative relatives.
They were always putting me down.
I blame my cynical neighbors.
They're just selfish, looking out for themselves.
Won't loan you.
Won't loan you money.
They were on my list.
I used to blame the economy.
I blame the community.
That's a pretty good list
for not doing well, isn't it?
I thought it was good.
I'll never forget one day.
Mr. Shoff is very kind,
but he was also very blunt.
And this was no exception.
And I'm glad he was blunt.
There's a lot of things I'd
have missed if he hadn't been blunt.
One day, with sort of a
curious look on his face, he said,
Jim, just out of curiosity, tell me,
how come you haven't done well up until now?
Excellent question.
I thought, well, so I won't look too bad,
I'll go through my list.
And this list I just gave
you, I put that on him.
And he was very patient.
He let me go through the whole thing,
the government, the weather.
I went through this whole thing.
When I finished,
he looked my list over very carefully.
He said, Mr. Rohn, big problem with your list.
You ain't on it.
How brilliant.
When I went to work
for him a few months later,
I learned very quickly to tear up my list,
reasons for not doing well,
and I threw it away.
And I got me a fresh piece of paper.
And I put one word on it.
Me.
There's a black heritage spiritual that says
it's not my mother, nor my father,
nor my brother, nor my sister,
but it's me, oh Lord,
standing in the need of prayer.
See, I used to blame everything outside.
And then let me give you a little philosophy
that helped turn my life around.
For your notes, here it is.
It's not what happens.
If you ask,
The only faith you need is
a little bit more time and deeply,
that determines the quality or the quantity of your life.
It's not what happens.
And the reason is because
what happens happens to about everybody.
No different.
The sun went down on all of us last night.
A common event, a happening.
And I found out that the same
things can happen to two different people.
One gets rich and one stays poor.
Why is that?
It's because it's not what happens, but rather,
it's what you do that changes everything.
So that's a key phrase.
It's not what happens.
It's what you do.
What happens is about the same.
You might put that in parentheses here.
Same.
What people do, that's what's different.
Anything can happen, right?
Everything can happen.
I've heard all the stories.
I've been one of the stories.
Hey, we could all tell stories all night long, right?
Happenings.
Anything can happen.
Have you heard of Murphy's laws?
Anybody here heard of Murphy's laws?
Okay, most of you have.
Murph had these laws.
One of them was, if
anything can go wrong, it will.
That's one of Murphy's laws.
He was not one of the
great positive speakers of the day.
But anyway, it's still true though, right?
Anything can go wrong.
Everything can go wrong.
For sure.
I've fallen out of the sky so many times.
Once to the tune of a couple of million.
Devastating.
Took me a while to survive that one.
Now, it wasn't all that much,
but it was all I had.
I mean, that's when it's much, right?
When it's all you got.
If you got three, two go.
You got one left.
You ain't looking that bad.
But when it all goes.
Has anybody been there when it all went?
Anybody?
Come on, the rest of you liars.
Go ahead.
Hey, we've all been there, right?
When it all went.
Of course, it used to
be a long time ago, right?
When you ran out of money,
got to zero, you were all through.
Heck, now you can whistle right on by zero, right?
They will bury you.
That's what they will do.
But see, those are the happenings, right?
Everything can happen.
Anything can happen.
But it's not the happenings.
It's what you do about it.
Somebody says, yeah, but you
don't understand the disappointments I've had.
Come on.
Everybody's had their share.
Disappointments are not special gifts reserved for the poor.
Everybody has them.
The difference is what you do about them.
It's not the weather.
I used to blame the weather.
And I discovered it rains on the rich.
So see, that won't help.
Two men wake up one morning.
There's a rainstorm on.
One of them looks out his
window, sees the rainstorm, and he says,
Wow, what a storm.
With weather like this, they can't expect
you to go out and make sales.
He stays home.
Same morning, the other guy looks out
his window, sees the same storm, says,
Wow, what a storm.
But he says, you know what?
With weather like this, what a great
day to go out and make sales.
Most everybody will probably
be home, especially the salesman.
See, that's the difference in how your life works out.
It's not what happens.
It's what you do.
So here's one of the key questions of the evening.
Starting tomorrow, what are you going to do
that will make a change in your life's direction?
Good question.
What are you going to do
starting tomorrow that will make a difference?
Now, see, if you don't know what
to do, you're going to do something.
If you don't know what to
do, you're going to do something.
If you don't do something starting tomorrow
that will make a difference, guess what?
It's going to be the same.
And see, that way you can guess what
the next five years are going to be like.
Look at the last five.
Because the next five are going to be like the
last five unless you made your key tomorrow, change it all.
Or change a little.
Or change something.
Or don't change.
It's choice time.
You can do whatever you want.
But it's nice to know any day
you wish, you can change your whole life.
What can you do starting
tomorrow that will make a difference?
Good question.
What can you do with economic chaos, massive disappointment?
What can you do with a broken heart?
What can you do and it won't work?
Good question.
What?
Or what?
Okay.
So what can you do?
What do you try to do?